<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dlkency.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://dlkency.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-14T17:13:48+00:00</updated><id>https://dlkency.github.io/feed.xml</id><subtitle>Research notes, blog posts, and projects on water, wildfire, and climate risk. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Natural-hazard Insurance 101</title><link href="https://dlkency.github.io/blog/2025/natural-hazard-insurance101/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Natural-hazard Insurance 101"/><published>2025-01-20T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-20T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dlkency.github.io/blog/2025/natural-hazard-insurance101</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dlkency.github.io/blog/2025/natural-hazard-insurance101/"><![CDATA[<p>(collected notes since I started my postdoc at the Institute for Risk Management and Insurance Innovation, UNC)</p> <p>I’ve pulled these thoughts together to help make sense of how flood, wildfire, hurricane and other natural-hazard insurance actually work in the U.S. — why prices are changing, who sets the rules, and what practical options exist if you live in a risky place.</p> <h2 id="big-picture-why-insurance-looks-different-across-states">Big picture: why insurance looks different across states</h2> <div style="background:#fff3b0; padding:10px; border-radius:6px"> Insurance in the U.S. is mostly a state-regulated business. That means each state decides how insurers operate, what policy forms are allowed, how and when companies can cancel or non-renew policies, and whether a state will create special “insurer of last resort” programs for homeowners who can’t find private coverage. </div> <p>A couple of headline facts that explain recent trends:</p> <p>• Average property insurance premiums have jumped sharply since 2020 (roughly a 30%+ rise on average), with the biggest increases concentrated where hazard exposure is highest — coastal hurricane zones and wildfire-prone areas. <br/> • One of the main drivers is <strong>higher reinsurance costs</strong>: insurers buy reinsurance to protect themselves from a single catastrophe wiping out their balance sheet, and when reinsurance gets more expensive, primary insurers pass some of that cost onto homeowners (see <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w32579">(Keys &amp; Mulder)</a>, Property Insurance and Disaster Risk, NBER WP 32579).</p> <h2 id="federal-vs-state-roles">Federal vs state roles</h2> <p>• Flood insurance is primarily federal (FEMA’s National Flood Insurance Program, NFIP), and <strong>flood coverage is not included in a standard homeowners policy</strong>. If you’re in a FEMA high-risk zone, lenders typically require NFIP or an accepted private alternative. <br/> • Other perils (wind, fire, hail, earthquake) are mostly handled by private insurers but regulated by states. States can also create residual-market pools (see examples below).</p> <h3 id="how-that-looks-on-the-ground">How that looks on the ground</h3> <p>• NFIP + private flood market (nationwide): <strong>NFIP remains the baseline for mortgage-required flood protection, but the private flood market has been growing as an alternative or complement to NFIP</strong>. <br/> • Florida — Citizens Property Insurance: an insurer of last resort that often takes in homeowners who can’t find private hurricane/wind/homeowners coverage. <br/> • Texas — TWIA: the Texas Windstorm Insurance Association provides wind/hail coverage for designated coastal counties where the private market withdraws. <br/> • California — FAIR Plan: a pooled “last-resort” program that offers basic fire coverage for properties private carriers won’t insure (often wildfire-exposed homes). <br/> • North Carolina has state programs that serve as backstops when the private market withdraws. Two state-run residual market programs: the North Carolina Joint Underwriting Association (NCJUA) — the state FAIR Plan that provides basic fire/property coverage where private insurers won’t — and the North Carolina Insurance Underwriting Association (NCIUA) / Coastal Property Insurance Pool (CPIP) that provides essential windstorm/coastal coverage for eligible coastal properties.</p> <h3 id="key-ways-states-differ-what-actually-changes-by-state">Key ways states differ (what actually changes by state)</h3> <ol> <li>Which residual/last-resort programs exist and how big they are — some states have large, politically important pools; others do not.</li> <li>Cancellation / nonrenewal rules and consumer protections — some state regulators limit nonrenewals after storms or impose notice and rate-review requirements.</li> <li>Which perils are excluded from a standard policy — e.g., flood and earthquake are normally excluded everywhere and require separate policies.</li> <li>Flood mapping, mandatory-purchase zones, and mitigation discounts — FEMA flood maps (FIRMs) drive mortgage requirements; communities that invest in mitigation can reduce NFIP rates through the Community Rating System.</li> <li>Availability and price of private flood and catastrophe products — private options are much more available in some markets than in others.</li> </ol> <h2 id="parametric-insurance-and-catastrophe-cat-bonds--new-tools-worth-knowing-about">Parametric insurance and catastrophe (CAT) bonds — new tools worth knowing about</h2> <h3 id="parametric-insurance--the-fast-objective-payout">Parametric insurance — the fast, objective payout</h3> <p>What it is: Parametric (or index-based) insurance pays when a predefined, measurable trigger is met — not when an adjuster assesses actual damage. Triggers are things like rainfall amount at a weather station, wind speed at a defined location, or earthquake magnitude within a defined radius. Why people like it • Speed: payouts can be disbursed quickly because they rely on objective measurements rather than slow damage inspections. That’s critical for liquidity after disasters. • Simplicity &amp; transparency: the contract specifies the trigger and the payout formula up front. • Tailorable: parametric products can be written for specific perils and exposures (e.g., a farmer’s drought policy tied to accumulated rainfall). Main downside — basis risk • Basis risk is the mismatch between the index and the actual loss a policyholder experiences. For example, heavy localized flooding that damages your house might not be captured by the nearest gauge used for the index — so you could suffer damage but receive no payout (or vice versa). Where parametrics are used • Parametric products are popular for rapid liquidity, for agriculture (drought/heat), and for public finance (quick funds to repair infrastructure). They’re increasingly paired with traditional indemnity insurance to reduce overall response time and funding gaps.</p> <h3 id="cat-bonds--transferring-risk-to-capital-markets">CAT bonds — transferring risk to capital markets</h3> <p>What it is: A catastrophe bond (CAT bond) is a financial security that transfers insured catastrophe risk from an insurer (or sponsor) to investors. If a specified catastrophe event occurs (defined by a trigger), the bond principal is used to pay claims; if not, investors receive interest and get their principal back at maturity.</p> <h3 id="why-insurers--governments-use-cat-bonds">Why insurers &amp; governments use CAT bonds</h3> <p>• Risk transfer / capacity: CAT bonds let insurers and governments access additional capital beyond reinsurance markets, especially for extreme events.<br/> • Diversification for investors: these bonds are attractive to investors because catastrophe risk is largely uncorrelated with financial markets (until a catastrophe hits). That means higher yield potential.<br/> Tradeoffs<br/> • Cost: issuing CAT bonds involves structuring and investor return costs — not always cheap for smaller exposures.<br/> • Trigger design &amp; basis risk: triggers must be carefully designed (indemnity triggers, parametric triggers, or modeled loss triggers). Poorly chosen triggers create basis risk for the sponsor or investors.<br/> • Complexity &amp; legal/credit risk: documentation, collateral mechanics, and post-event verification add complexity.<br/> How the pieces fit together <br/> • Parametric insurance and CAT bonds are complementary tools. A government or insurer might buy parametric coverage to get fast liquidity and then issue CAT bonds to shift residual tail risk to capital markets. Innovations in parametrics (better sensors and modeling) are improving both the reliability of payouts and the triggers used in CAT-bond structures.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/w32579_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/w32579_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/w32579_1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/w32579_1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Rising Home Insurance Premiums (source: NBER working paper 32579 / CoreLogic). </div> <div style="background:#fff3b0; padding:10px; border-radius:6px"> Insurance markets have tightened sharply in recent years: inflation-adjusted homeowner premiums rose roughly 20% between 2020 and 2023, while catastrophe reinsurance costs spiked during the 2023 renewals—raising carriers’ expenses and eroding market capacity. As a result, some insurers are pulling back or non-renewing policies in the riskiest states, leaving many homeowners stuck with residual-market plans (FAIR/Citizens) that are often pricier and more limited. Policymakers and markets are experimenting with tools like parametric insurance and catastrophe bonds to broaden capacity and speed payouts after disasters, but the sector needs real innovation and smarter regulation to keep coverage affordable and resilient. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="natural"/><category term="hazard;"/><category term="insurance;"/><category term="state"/><category term="policies"/><category term="insurance"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[how natural hazard insurance differs across US states]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Water Issues - A Financial Perspective</title><link href="https://dlkency.github.io/blog/2024/table-of-contents/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Water Issues - A Financial Perspective"/><published>2024-11-20T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-20T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dlkency.github.io/blog/2024/table-of-contents</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dlkency.github.io/blog/2024/table-of-contents/"><![CDATA[<p>Since the dawn of human civilization, we have competed for resources, and those who succeed in securing them are able to grow their communities and enhance their competitive edge. Among these resources, water is not only essential for human survival but also crucial for economic, agricultural, and technological development. As the famous saying goes, “Whoever controls the water, controls the West.” In this post, I want to discuss the issue of water scarcity and explore whether financial solutions can effectively address this challenge.</p> <h2 id="institutional-complexity-of-californias-water-system">Institutional Complexity of California’s Water System</h2> <p>Navigating California’s water system is like solving a unique puzzle. The state’s water rights are governed by a dual system: riparian and appropriative rights. Riparian rights let those with land next to water use it, while appropriative rights follow a “first come, first served” rule, regardless of where your land is.</p> <p>Now, throw in California’s geography, and things get even more interesting. Most of the water is up north, thanks to those impressive mountain ranges storing it all. But here’s the kicker: the south, with its desert vibes, is where you’ll find bustling hotspots like Los Angeles and Hollywood. It’s a real head-scratcher-how do these thriving areas keep going in such a dry zone? This is the heart of California’s water conundrum: figuring out how to quench the thirst of its most vital regions that naturally lack water.</p> <h2 id="californias-agricultural-economy">California’s Agricultural Economy</h2> <p>Many people might not realize that California boasts the largest agricultural output of any state in the U.S. It produces high-value crops like almonds and pistachios, which are almost exclusively grown in California, meeting 99% of the nation’s demand. But behind this agricultural success story is a complex challenge: managing water, especially given the state’s intricate water rights system.</p> <p>California’s water resources are subject to periodic droughts and floods, making effective management a constant challenge. For example, in 2023, Tulare Lake, a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2024/mar/24/california-tulare-lake-shrinking">“zombie lake”</a> reemerged after disappearing 130 years ago due to one of the wettest years on record. The current infrastructure struggled to handle the excess water, leading to significant flooding in the Tulare Basin’s <a href="https://fresnoland.org/2023/03/27/flooding-out-other-farmers-was-premeditated-by-the-powerful-j-g-boswell-company-one-farmer-asserts/#:~:text=What's%20at%20stake%3F-,Flooding%20over%20miles%20of%20farmland%20north%20and%20east%20of%20the,lake%20first%20which%20would%20have">farmlands</a>, where many high-value crops are cultivated. This highlights the ongoing struggle to balance water supply with agricultural demands in California.</p> <h2 id="navigating-the-ups-and-downs-of-cash-flow-in-californias-water-world">Navigating the Ups and Downs of Cash Flow in California’s Water World</h2> <p>For water users like irrigation districts and major metropolitan areas, the rollercoaster ride of water supply can mean big headaches: reduced revenue and skyrocketing costs. When drought hits and water is scarce, the state simply allocates less to contractors. This includes major urban centers like Los Angeles and agricultural irrigation districts. During these dry years, cities receive less water, and irrigation districts struggle to sell enough water to large-scale farms. They often have to turn to the often expensive spot market to meet demand.</p> <p>Consider the Nasdaq Veles California Water Price Index <a href="https://indexes.nasdaqomx.com/Index/History/NQH2O">(NQH2O)</a> -an index for tracking water costs in the state. During the exceptionally dry year of 2022, prices soared to $1,200 per acre-foot, six times higher than in wetter years! You can imagine the financial strain on cities and farms. Beyond just higher bills, these pressures can result in staff layoffs, reduced spending on critical infrastructure maintenance, and potentially lead to credit rating downgrades and increased borrowing costs when districts and cities issue debt.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/NQH2O-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/NQH2O-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/NQH2O-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/NQH2O.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Historical CA water prices (source: Nasdaq Veles California Water Price Index). </div> <p>So, how do they manage this financial tightrope? Stability is key, and some solutions include using financial derivatives like futures and options to lock in prices or purchasing insurance to guard against extreme losses. Of course, these strategies depend heavily on accurately predicting hydrologic conditions and understanding the financial implications - a topic I’m diving into in my upcoming papers. Stay tuned!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="water"/><category term="agricultural-cconomy"/><category term="water"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[the issue of water scarcity from financial perspective]]></summary></entry></feed>